<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pip on Pradyun Gedam</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/tags/pip/</link><description>Recent content in pip on Pradyun Gedam</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pradyunsg.me/tags/pip/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>pip 24.1 betas -- help us test a major upcoming change!</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2024/05/13/pip-24/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2024/05/13/pip-24/</guid><description>The pip team has released pip 24.1b1 which contains a lot of significant improvements and bug fixes.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to highlight a major change in this blog post: the removal of support for &amp;ldquo;legacy&amp;rdquo; versions and dependency specification, or as I like to call it, nonsensical versions and dependencies. We&amp;rsquo;re releasing this as a beta to get feedback from the community on how this change affects their workflows.
Nonsensical versions and dependencies For a bunch of historical reasons, pip has allowed many arbitrary strings as versions and dependency specification.</description></item><item><title>Testing the next-gen pip dependency resolver</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2020/03/27/pip-resolver-testing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2020/03/27/pip-resolver-testing/</guid><description>This is an attempt to summarize the broader software architecture around dependency resolution in pip and how testing is being done around this area.
The motivation behind writing this, is to make sure all the developers working on this project are on the same page, and to have a written record about the state of affairs.
Architecture The &amp;ldquo;legacy&amp;rdquo; resolver in pip, is implemented as part of pip&amp;rsquo;s codebase and has been a part of it for many years.</description></item></channel></rss>