<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Python packaging on Pradyun Gedam</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/tags/python-packaging/</link><description>Recent content in Python packaging on Pradyun Gedam</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pradyunsg.me/tags/python-packaging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>PDM does not implement PEP 582</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/21/pdm-does-not-implement-pep-582/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/21/pdm-does-not-implement-pep-582/</guid><description>PDM claims to implement PEP 582. However, if you look at what it implements, it is something completely different from the standard.
PDM&amp;rsquo;s file system structure &amp;lt;root&amp;gt; __pypackages__ 3.10 bottle myscript.py PEP 582&amp;rsquo;s file system structure &amp;lt;root&amp;gt; __pypackages__ lib python3.10 site-packages bottle myscript.py Why does this matter? Well, outside of the issues with implementing draft proposals in workflow tooling, I think this is reflective of the issues with the competitive nature of the Python packaging ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s workflow tooling space.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on the Python packaging ecosystem</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/21/thoughts-on-python-packaging/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/21/thoughts-on-python-packaging/</guid><description>My response to the discussion topic posed in Python Packaging Strategy Discussion Part 1 had become quite long, so I decided to move it to write a blog post instead. This post then started absorbing various draft posts I&amp;rsquo;ve had on this topic since this blog was started, morphing to include my broader thoughts on where we are today.
TL;DR This post is a bit long, so here&amp;rsquo;s the key points I&amp;rsquo;m making:</description></item><item><title>How the Python Packaging community is organised</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/14/python-packaging-organisation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2023/01/14/python-packaging-organisation/</guid><description>The way the Python packaging community is organised is something that I&amp;rsquo;ve explained in multiple places, in multiple contexts. I figure that it&amp;rsquo;ll be useful to actually write it down in a single place, so that I don&amp;rsquo;t have to repeat myself.
The Python Packaging Authority The Python Packaging Authority (PyPA) is a fairly loose group of projects that happen to be related to Python packaging. While the PyPA has a formal governance model, there&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;ldquo;oversight&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;enforcement&amp;rdquo; on projects that are part of the PyPA &amp;ndash; they are only required to adopt the PSF Code of Conduct and to be accepted by the existing members.</description></item><item><title>Wheels are faster, even for pure Python packages</title><link>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2022/12/31/wheels-are-faster-pure-python/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pradyunsg.me/blog/2022/12/31/wheels-are-faster-pure-python/</guid><description>When installing with pip (or from PyPI in general), wheels are much faster than source distributions, even for pure-Python projects.
Packages with native code are a clearer win, because the wheel file will contain pre-compiled binaries for the platform you&amp;rsquo;re installing on. This means that you don&amp;rsquo;t need to have a compiler and non-Python build dependencies installed, and you don&amp;rsquo;t need to wait for the compiler to do its thing.</description></item></channel></rss>